Conference on Problems of American Foreign Policy records, 1950-1961 C241
Indiana University Archives
Conference on Problems of American Foreign Policy records
1950-1961
1950-1956
Indiana University Archives
Indiana University. President
C241
1 cubic foot
This series of conferences was held annually at Indiana University from 1950 through 1956. They were organized by a committee under the general direction of the university president's office in cooperation with the U.S. Dept. of State and with funding from the Lilly Endowment. Collection consists of correspondence, financial records, working papers, invitations, programs, and publicity materials.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Advance notice is required.
Administrative History
This series of conferences was held annually at IU from 1950 through 1956. It was organized by a committee under the general direction of the office of President Herman B Wells in co-operation with the US Department of State, and with funding from the Lilly Endowment. The primary organizational work was done by Peter Fraenkel of the President's office and Austin V. Clifford of the Law School. Others who were active in organizing the conferences included Edward Buehrig, Department of Government; Frank Lee Benns, Department of History; and John T. Hays, of Hays & Hays Law Firm.
The conferences sought to bring State Department officials together with academic and civic leaders from the Midwest for frank discussions of current foreign policy problems. In this they were successful. However, recognizing that they were not moving beyond discussions of current events to the deeper issues of the nature and purpose of foreign policy per se, the committee determined to end the conference in its current form in the spring of 1957. Planning for a renewed conference continued into 1960, but none was held.
Arrangement
Records organized into one series, Administrative files, and then further organized into nine subseries representing each planned conference.
Scope and Content Note
These files were generated by various IU participants, but seem to be primarily those of the President's office. An inventory was made in 1994, and duplicate printed material was discarded, but no attempt was made to reorganize the material within the folders. During processing, working papers were unified, financial records combined, correspondence related to planning and organization was separated from invitations and correspondence with guests, and the records arranged in chronological order. The records are organized into one series, Administrative files. Each conference represents a sub-series. Within each sub-series, folders contain working papers, organizational correspondence, invitations and related correspondence, programs and packets, requisitions and vouchers, and publicity and news clippings, all in chronological order.
Acquisition Information
Accession 1059
United States --Foreign relations --1945-1953 --Congresses.; United States --Foreign relations --1953-1961 --Congresses.; Conference on Problems of American Foreign Policy (1950-1956) (Indiana University); Conference on Problems of American Foreign Policy (1950-1956) (Indiana University) -- Records and correspondence; Conference on Problems of American Foreign Policy (1950-1956) (Indiana University) -- History -- Sources; Conference on Problems of American Foreign Policy (1950-1956) (Indiana University) -- Archives
- Administrative files, 1950-1961 (Box 1)
  - Conference on Problems of American Foreign Policy, 22-24 June 1950
    - Working papers, 22 Apr. 1950 – 13 Sep. 1950; undated (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 13 Feb. 1950 – 25 Jun. 1950; undated (Box 1)
    - Invitations, 6 Jun. 1950 – 30 Jul. 1950 (Box 1)
    - Requisitions and vouchers, 9 Jun. 1950 – 9 Aug. 1950 (Box 1)
    - Agendas, publicity and programs, 18 Jun. 1950 – 27 Jun. 1950; undated (Box 1)
  - 2nd Conference on Problems of American Foreign Policy, 20-21 July 1951
    - Working papers (Fraenkel's files), 2 Feb. 1951 – 24 Aug. 1951; undated (Box 1)
    - Correspondence, 30 Jan. 1951 – 18 Dec. 1951; undated (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Wells, Clifford, Fraenkel), 17 May 1951 – 23 Jul. 1951 (Box 1)
    - Invitations, rosters, and administrative arrangements, July 1951; undated (Box 1)
    - Requisitions and vouchers, 18 Jul. 1951 – 20 Sep. 1951 (Box 1)
    - Agendas, publicity and publications, Summer 1950 – Summer 1951; undated (Box 1)
  - 3rd Conference on Problems of American Foreign Policy, 11-12 July 1952
    - Correspondence, 28 Aug. 1951 – 6 Aug. 1952; undated (Box 1)
    - Correspondence (Fraenkel's file), 22 Jun. 1952 – 10 Sep. 1952; undated (Box 1)
    - Programs, rosters, packets, undated (Box 1)
    - Requisitions and vouchers, 3 Jul. 1953 – 12 Nov. 1953 (Box 1)
  - 4th Conference on Problems of American Foreign Policy, 10-11 July 1953
    - Correspondence, 1 Dec. 1952 – 10 Sep. 1953; undated (Box 1)
    - Pamphlets, agendas, press release, undated (Box 1)
    - Receipts and vouchers, 3 Jul. 1953 – 12 Nov. 1953 (Box 1)
  - 5th Conference on Problems of American Foreign Policy, 9-10 July 1954
    - Correspondence, 28 Sep. 1953 – 14 Oct. 1954; undated (Box 1)
    - General correspondence (Fraenkel's file), 18 Mar. 1954 – 14 Sep. 1954; undated (Box 1)
    - Requisitions and vouchers, 11 May 1954 – 20 Jul. 1954 (Box 1)
    - Agendas, news clippings, guest book, October 1953 – 29 Jul. 1954; undated (Box 1)
  - 6th Conference on Problems of American Foreign Policy, 24-25 June 1955
    - Acknowledged correspondence (Fraenkel's file), 9 Nov. 1954 – 18 Aug. 1955; undated (Box 1)
    - General correspondence, 9 Nov. 1954 – 8 Apr. 1955; undated (Box 1)
    - "Conference on Values" materials from general correspondence, 5 May 1958 (sic) (Box 1)
    - Vouchers, news clippings, 26 Apr. 1955 – 30 Aug. 1955 (Box 1)
  - 7th Conference on Problems of American Foreign Policy, 29-30 June 1956
    - Correspondence, 28 Jun. 1955 – 7 Dec. 1956; undated (Box 1)
    - Vouchers and receipts, 13 Jan. 1956 – 28 Aug. 1956 (Box 1)
  - 1957 Conference on Problems of American Foreign Policy (cancelled)
    - Correspondence, receipts, 3 Jul. 1956 – 18 Jun. 1957; undated (Box 1)
  - Conference on Problems of American Foreign Policy (not held)
    - Correspondence, account statements, 31 Oct. 1959 – 28 Feb. 1961 (Box 1)